

To this number should be added 6000 that have been inoculated by Mr. Sutton’s assistants, as he taught them his method, and as they use none but his medicines. So that he may be said to have inoculated, within these three years, 20000 persons.

C. for the Cr. How many of this number have died in consequence of inoculation?

Houlton. Not one.

C. for the Prisoner. I think you said that you was officiating clergyman to the Prisoner?

Houlton. I did say so.

C. for the Prisoner. And pray, Sir, what was your office?

Houlton. To pray with the sick, and return thanks for their recovery.

C. for the Prisoner. Very extraordinary, truly. Give me leave to ask you, whence you took this very exact account of the number of persons inoculated by the Prisoner?

Houlton. From Mr. Sutton’s books.

Couns. for the Prisoner. I beg,[Pg 7] gentlemen of the jury, you will observe that this account of the number of persons inoculated, and consequently of the number of lives preserved, one of the crimes of which the Prisoner stands accused, was taken only from his own books. This is a material circumstance, and I make no doubt but you will give it its due weight.

Couns. for the Cr. Have you any other question to ask this witness?

Couns. for the Prisoner. I have done.

Couns. for the Cr. We are perfectly satisfied, Mr. Houlton, with your accurate account of the number of people inoculated by the Prisoner. Now, Sir, let me ask you a few questions relative to the Prisoner’s peculiar method of communicating the infection. How is this performed?

Houlton. By means of a puncture so slight, that it is scarce felt by the patient, and which in a minute afterwards is scarce visible.

[Pg 8]

Couns. for the Cr. What do you know of his medicines?

Houlton. I know that they are most powerful. If he perceives a symptom in patients of a great fever, or a probability of their having more pustules than they would chuse, he quickly prevents both by virtue of his medicines.

Couns. for the Cr. Do you recollect any particular instance of this extraordinary virtue of his medicines?

Houlton. I do. A child belonging to Mr. Barnard, of Waltham in Essex, was seized with the natural small pox. As soon as it was discovered, by the pustules making a plentiful appearance, the child was conveyed to one of Mr. Sutton’s houses. The next morning, the face and body being extremely full, Mr. Sutton marked with a pen a great number of pustules, and administered the medicine I allude to: some hours afterwards, hundreds of the pustules disappeared; and among them several of those[Pg 9] marked leaving the little dot on the plain surface of the skin. The child did extremely well.

Couns. for the Cr. Sir, you may retire.

Dr. George Baker sworn.

Couns. for the Cr. Pray, Dr. Baker, inform the Court what you know concerning the Prisoner’s practice of inoculation.

Dr. Baker. I can give the Court but little information from my own knowledge; but what I have to say, I received from a gentleman, whose accuracy in observing, as well as veracity in relating what he observed, may be relied on. All persons are obliged to go through a strict preparatory regimen for a fortnight before the operation. During this course, all fermented liquors and animal food, except milk, are forbid. Fruit is generally allowed, except on the days of purging. A powder is given three several times, and a dose of purging[Pg 10] salt on the following morning. The composition of this powder is a secret. But that it contains mercury is evident, from its having salivated some patients.

Couns. for the Cr. I beg, gentlemen of the jury, you will please to remember that the Doctor says, the composition of the powder is a secret. Now, Sir, please to proceed to his manner of communicating the disease.

Dr. Baker. The operator opens a pustule on the arm of some patient in whom the matter is yet in a crude state; and then with his moist lancet just raises the cuticle on the arm of the person to be inoculated, applying neither plaister nor bandage. This was his method some time ago; but he now generally dips his lancet only in the moisture issuing from the place of incision, before the eruption, four days after the operation.

Couns. for the Cr. And pray, Sir, what medicines does he give after the operation?

Dr. Baker. On the night following,[Pg 11] the patient takes a pill, which is repeated every other night till the fever comes on.

Couns. for the Cr. Do you know the composition of this pill?

Dr. Baker. No: it is a secret.

Couns. for the Cr. Are the patients confined to their apartments at this period?

Dr. Baker. No: moderate exercise in the open air is strongly recommended.

Couns. for the Cr. Now, Sir, please to inform the Court what you have learnt concerning the progress of the disease and the manner of treating it.

Dr. Baker. Three days after the operation, if it succeed, there appears on the incision a spot, like a flea bite, not as yet above the skin, which gradually becomes first a red pimple, and then a bladder full of clear lymph, advancing to maturation with the pustules. In proportion as the discolouration round the place of incision is[Pg 12] greater, the less quantity of eruption is expected; therefore, when this circle is small, stronger and more frequent cathartics are exhibited. If, when the fever comes on, there appears no tendency to perspiration, some acid drops, or more powerful sudorifics, are administered. In general, during the burning heat of the fever, he gives cold water; but after the perspiration begins, warm baum-tea, or water-gruel. As soon as the sweat abates, the eruption having appeared, he obliges every body to get up, to walk about the house, or into the garden. From this time, to the turn of the disease, he gives milk-gruel ad libitum. On the following day he gives a dose of Glauber’s salts, and, if the eruption be considerable, he repeats it on the third day.

Couns. for the Cr. Pray, Sir, can you give the Court any information relative to the number of persons that have been inoculated by the Prisoner and his assistants?

[Pg 13]

Dr. Baker. According to the best information that I can procure, about seventeen thousand have been thus inoculated, of which number no more than five or six have died.

Mr. B. Chandler sworn.

Couns. for the Cr. You, Sir, I think are a surgeon at Canterbury?

Mr. Chandler. I am.

Couns. for the Cr. Pray, Mr. Chandler, can you give us any information concerning the Prisoner’s success in the practice of inoculation?

Mr. Chandler. I know nothing of Mr. Sutton’s own particular practice, except from report. What I have to say relates only to that of one of his assistants, or partners.

President. This evidence cannot affect the Prisoner at the bar, as he tells you he knows nothing of Mr. Sutton’s own particular practice.

Couns. for the Cr. I beg your pardon, Mr. President, the Prisoner[Pg 14] at the bar stands indicted for preserving the lives of the King’s subjects, not only by inoculating, but also causing to be inoculated.

President. Proceed to his examination.

Couns. for the Cr. Pray, Mr. Chandler, who is this assistant or partner, with whose practice you are acquainted?

Mr. Chandler. He is a surgeon of eminence at Maidstone; his name is Peale.

Couns. for the Cr. Where was it that you saw his practice?

Mr. Chandler. In the city of Canterbury.

Couns. for the Cr. What number of persons might he inoculate in that city?

Mr. Chandler. I cannot exactly tell; but it is considerable.

Couns. for the Cr. Did any of his patients die under inoculation?

Mr. Chandler. Not that I know of.

[Pg 15]

Couns. for the Cr. Did you hear Dr. Baker’s evidence?

Mr. Chandler. I did.

Couns. for the Cr. Does Mr. Peale’s practice differ in any respect from that of the Prisoner, as related by the Doctor?

Mr. Chandler. It differs in some few particulars.

Couns. for the Cr. What are these particulars?

Mr. Chandler. I think, Dr. Baker informed the Court that the persons to be inoculated are a fortnight under preparation. That time is now reduced to eight days. The pill is not given every other night, as mentioned by the Doctor; many of Mr. Peale’s patients not having taken it till the fifth day after inoculation. It is generally repeated on the seventh day, and sometimes continued to the eighth or ninth. When the eruptive fever comes on, a sort of julap is given to be drank ad libitum; composed of a small quantity of a medicine nearly[Pg 16] the colour of Madeira wine, poured into a quart or pint bottle of spring water. It’s taste is very agreeable, cooling, and sub-acid. And here my observations differ most from the accounts related to Dr. Baker; for though this medicine, if taken upon going to bed, did sometimes seem to occasion a slight perspiration, yet an increased perspiration was never, that I saw, or could learn, insisted on in the day, much less a profuse sweat at any time: for none of the patients are allowed to lie in bed, or sit over the fire, or keep within doors, if the weather is tolerable, even during the feverish symptoms, and the only drink allowed is toast and water.

Couns. for the Prisoner. I thought, Sir, you said that the patients were allowed a certain sub-acid julap ad libitum? and now you tell us, that the only drink allowed is toast-water. I beg, gentlemen of the jury, you will observe that he contradicts himself.

Mr. Chandler. When I said that[Pg 17] toast-water was the only drink allowed, I certainly mean to except the julap, which I considered as a medicine, and the toast-water as common drink.

Couns. for the Prisoner. I submit it to the Court, whether he did not contradict himself.

President. He has explained his meaning sufficiently.

C. for the Prisoner. I submit. Mr. Chandler, we desire you will not leave the Court; we shall ask you a few more questions by and by.

C. for the Pris. Pray, Mr. Chandler, let me ask you, whether you know the composition of the medicines given by Mr. Peale?

Mr. Chandler. I do not.

Couns. for the Pris. You do not. Then they are secret medicines?

Mr. Chandler. They are.

Couns. for the Pris. Sir, we have done with you. Mr. President, and gentlemen of the jury, this is all the evidence we shall produce in support of our indictment. Though it[Pg 18] were easy to corroborate every thing they have said by a hundred witnesses; yet as these are more than the law requires, as their evidence is so clear and circumstantial, and as they are gentlemen of undoubted character, we think it totally unnecessary to trouble you with the repetition of facts, of the truth of which you cannot possibly doubt.

That the Prisoner at the bar is guilty of preserving the lives of his Majesty’s liege subjects, we have proved, first, on the evidence of the Rev. Mr. Houlton, who asserts, that in the space of three years, he, the Prisoner, hath inoculated, or caused to be inoculated, no less than twenty thousand persons. Now, in the old way of inoculation, if we allow that there died one in two hundred, which I believe is about the mark, it will appear, that he hath actually preserved the lives of one hundred people; for in the twenty thousand inoculated by the Prisoner and his accomplices,[Pg 19] not one hath died, whose death could be justly attributed to inoculation. This witness hath likewise informed you, that the Prisoner is actually possessed of a certain medicine, by the administration of which, and by the help of a magick circle drawn with a pen round the pustules, together with a prayer composed and repeated by this witness on the occasion, he can make them retire at the word of command, with the same dexterity, and in the same manner, as any other Hocus Pocus commands his little balls to pass through the table. That this is performed by means unknown to the faculty, is very evident, as not one of them all pretends to any thing like it.

Dr. Baker, a physician of considerable reputation, after giving you a clear account of the Prisoner’s extraordinary method of preparing, and manner of treating his patients thro’ the whole progress of the disease, sufficiently confirms the evidence of Mr.[Pg 20] Houlton, in regard to the number of persons inoculated; with whom he also agrees in confirming that material part of our allegation, which accuses the Prisoner of performing these miracles by means of secret medicines, and unusual modes of practice.

Our last witness, Mr. Chandler, a very skilful surgeon, hath, in the course of his examination, corroborated Dr. Baker’s account of the Prisoner’s unprecedented mode of practice, at least in the most essential points; so that you cannot possibly entertain the least doubt as to facts. Gentlemen, it were very easy for me to expatiate on the fatal consequences of permitting such proceedings to go unpunished; but your own understanding and impartiality will, I make no doubt, prompt you to determine with propriety: I therefore forbear to say any thing more that might influence your judgement. The counsel for the Prisoner may now call their evidence whenever they think proper.

[Pg 21]

Couns. for the Prisoner. Mr. President, and gentlemen of the jury, the Prisoner at the bar stands indicted for preserving the lives of his Majesty’s liege subjects, by secret medicines and modes of practice, and by inoculating, or causing to be inoculated, divers persons, &c. With regard to his preserving the lives of the King’s subjects, it has been so insufficiently proved, that we shall not take up your time in disproving it; but as to his secret medicines, we shall shew you that the ingredients of which they are made are certainly known, and consequently that they are not secret medicines. We shall prove to you, by undeniable evidence, that the same medicines have been long recommended and administered for the same purposes, and with equal success. And we shall, last of all, produce a witness of unquestionable authority, who will convince you that the successful practice of inoculation does not depend on any peculiar medicine whatsoever, and[Pg 22] consequently that the Prisoner is perfectly guiltless of the crimes of which he stands accused. Call Dr. Thomas Ruston.

Dr. Thomas Ruston sworn.

Pray, Dr. Ruston, have you any knowledge of the composition of certain medicines used by the Prisoner at the bar, in his practice of inoculation?

Dr. Ruston. I believe I have.

Couns. for the Pris. What is the form of these medicines?

Dr. Ruston. Powders, pills, and drops.

Couns. for the Prisoner. What are the ingredients which compose the powder?

Dr. Ruston. I verily believe the powder to consist entirely of calomel and æthiops mineral.

Couns. for the Pris. What are your reasons for thinking so?

Dr. Ruston. My reasons are founded[Pg 23] on chemical experiment and analogy.

Couns. for the Prisoner. What experiment and what analogy?

Dr. Ruston. 1st. To a small quantity of Mr. Sutton’s powder, which was of a greyish colour, I added a few drops of volatile alkali, which immediately changed it to a deep black. 2dly. To a small quantity of the same, a few drops of a solution of salt of tartar were added, which produced the same colour. 3dly. A few drops of lime-water were added, which also changed the powder black, but not quite so black as in experiment 1 and 2. The colour and weight of Mr. Sutton’s powder were exactly imitated by the addition of six grains of æthiops to ten grains of calomel, and by repeating the above experiments with this composition, it was found to exhibit exactly the same phenomena.

Couns. for the Prisoner. Now, Sir, as to the pills?

[Pg 24]

Dr. Ruston. The pills, from their smell, taste, colour, and effects, are evidently no other than the well-known pilulæ cochiæ, with a small addition of calomel.

Couns. for the Prisoner. Did you make no experiment with the pills?

Dr. Ruston. Yes. I poured on one of them a few drops of volatile alkali, and it immediately struck a deep black. The same appearance was produced by salt of tartar, and by lime-water. I then added a few grains of calomel to the pilulæ cochiæ, and repeated the experiments with the same effect.

Couns. for the Prisoner. And what discoveries have you made concerning the drops?

Dr. Ruston. The acid drops with which he prepares his punch, is so obviously of the same nature with the dulcified volatile vitriolic acid that arises during the distillation of æther, and which is the same with what exists in large quantities in the liquor anodinus[Pg 25] of Hoffman, that it was unnecessary to submit it to any chemical experiment. There was nothing foreign in its composition.

Couns. for the Cr. Not to interrupt the course of your examination, I beg leave, before you proceed, to ask the Doctor one question. If I remember right, you said, the powder contained ten grains of calomel. Pray, Doctor, is not this an unusual large dose?

Dr. Ruston. As an alterative it certainly is so; and therefore Mr. Sutton’s powders have often been known to salivate the patient. But its activity is somewhat weakened by the sulphur contained in the æthiops.

Couns. for the Cr. But has it not been generally supposed that there was some other powerful ingredient in Mr. Sutton’s medicines?

Dr. Ruston. Yes, antimony. But from my experiments, I am convinced of the contrary.

Couns. for the Pris. Now, Doctor, give me leave to ask you, whether the exhibition[Pg 26] of mercury, as preparative to inoculation, be the invention of the Prisoner at the bar?

Dr. Ruston. Certainly not.

Couns. for the Pris. Who were the inventors of this practice?

Dr. Ruston. I cannot answer positively to that question. The great Boerhaave, in his Aphorisms, recommended the experiment of uniting mercury with antimony as an antidote to the variolous virus; but I believe some American physicians were the first who used mercury in preparing for inoculation.

Couns. for the Pris. And with what success?

Dr. Ruston. With very great. Out of the first three thousand inoculated, only five died; and these were all children, who could not be prevailed on to take the medicine.

Couns. for the Pris. I beg, gentlemen of the jury, you will remember this circumstance—All that took the mercurial medicines recovered.[Pg 27] Pray, Dr. Ruston, was this new method of preparation long confined to any particular physician, or part of America?

Dr. Ruston. No: the fame of its extraordinary success soon produced a number of inoculators on the new plan; so that in a short time it spread from one end of the continent to the other.

Couns. for the Pris. Did these several inoculators all give precisely the same medicines?

Dr. Ruston. Not precisely.

Couns. for the Pris. In what respect do they differ?

Dr. Ruston. Principally in the proportions of calomel and antimony.

Couns. for the Pris. But they all agreed in giving calomel?

Dr. Ruston. All.

Couns. for the Pris. Did they agree in any other respect?

Dr. Ruston. Yes: they all gave cathartics, and during the eruptive fever[Pg 28] treated their patients in the anti-phlogistic method.

Couns. for the Pris. Were their patients under any restrictions in regard to diet?

Dr. Ruston. In general they were ordered to abstain from salt food, spirituous liquors, butter, oil, and such like.

Couns. for the Pris. You have given a very satisfactory account of these matters. Now give me leave to ask, whether you yourself practise inoculation?

Dr. Ruston. I do.

Couns. for the Pris. Do you prepare your patients?

Dr. Ruston. Certainly.

Couns. for the Pris. Do you confine your patients to any particular diet?

Dr. Ruston. I order them to abstain from animal food, spirituous liquors, and spices.

Couns. for the Pris. And what medicines do you prescribe?

[Pg 29]

Dr. Ruston. They consist principally of mercurials and antimonials.

Couns. for the Pris. Do you believe there is any specific virtue in these medicines? Do you give them as antidotes?

Dr. Ruston. By no means. I give them merely as evacuants, and accordingly proportion them to the constitution and age of the patient.

Couns. for the Pris. Can you say any thing, from experience, of the success of your method, compared with that of the Prisoner at the bar?

Dr. Ruston. I can say, from experience, that my method, in point of success, is fully equal to his.

Couns. for the Pris. What is your opinion of his cold regimen?

Dr. Ruston. I approve of it in general, and practise it; but not in the extreme.

Couns. for the Pris. What is your opinion as to the manner of communicating the infection?

[Pg 30]

Dr. Ruston. I think it a matter of little importance. That of just raising the skin with the point of a lancet, which has been dipped into a pustule, and then rubbing the matter which adheres to it on the wound with the finger, seems to be as good a one as any.

Couns. for the Pris. One question more. Do you think, upon the whole, that the Prisoner at the bar possesses any secret, to which his success is to be attributed?

Dr. Ruston. I think it must have appeared, from the evidence I have given, that he possesses no secret at all.

Couns. for the Pris. We shall now recall one of their own witnesses; a gentleman of undoubted veracity; whose evidence, if it have proved any thing against the Prisoner, will, upon farther examination, be found to prove much more in his favour.

[Pg 31]

Dr. Baker.

Pray, Dr. Baker, is the practice of preparing persons for the small pox with calomel peculiar to the Prisoner at the bar?

Dr. Baker. By no means: it is a very general practice. There are several physicians of credit who insist strenuously on its good effects.

Couns. for the Pris. Is it common to give purgative medicines on this occasion?

Dr. Baker. That in general two or three doses of some purging medicine ought to be given, almost all inoculators have agreed.

Couns. for the Pris. Now, Dr. Baker, give me leave to ask you, as a physician, whether it be your opinion that the marvellous success, of which the Prisoner stands accused, be owing to the peculiar virtue of any medicine or medicines, known only to himself and his accomplices?

[Pg 32]

Dr. Baker. I am of opinion it is not.

Couns. for the Pris. To what cause then do you ascribe that success?

Dr. Baker. Principally to the free use of cold air.

Couns for the Pris. Is he the only inoculator who allows his patients the free use of cold air?

Dr. Baker. Not now: the practice is at present very general in many parts of this kingdom.

Couns. for the Pris. Was he the inventor of this cold regimen?

Dr. Baker. I cannot accuse him of being the inventor, because it is strenuously recommended, in the natural small pox, by writers of the first rank, particularly Sydenham, whose works are in the hands of every physician.

Couns. for the Pris. We shall now call a physician sufficiently known in the medical world, particularly by his Analysis of Inoculation.

[Pg 33]

Dr. Kirkpatrick sworn.

Couns. for the Pris. I think, Sir, you have had much experience in the practice of inoculation?

Dr. Kirkpatrick. I have.

Couns. for the Pris. Have you been long accustomed to give calomel in preparing your patients?

Dr. Kirkpatrick. It hath long been my practice, as appears from my book.

Couns. for the Pris. Has it been your practice to confine your patients to any particular regimen?

Dr. Kirkpatrick. It appears from my Analysis, that I regulate my practice, in this respect, according to age and constitution; but in general I advise that they should abstain from flesh meat, spirituous liquors, and, in short, every thing inflammatory, or difficult of digestion.

Couns. for the Pris. I beg, gentlemen of the jury, you will take notice that the Doctor prescribes a vegetable[Pg 34] diet; so that this is no new thing. Pray, Doctor, when was your Analysis printed?

Dr. Kirkpatrick. The first edition, in the last King’s reign, and the second in the year 1761.

Dr. Benjamin Gale sworn.

Couns. for the Pris. You are a physician, I think?

Dr. Gale. I am.

Couns. for the Pris. Where do you live?

Dr. Gale. At Connecticut in New England.

Couns. for the Pris. Have you practised inoculation?

Dr. Gale. I have inoculated many hundreds.

Couns. for the Pris. Do you prepare your patients with calomel?

Dr. Gale. I do.

Couns. for the Pris. With what success?

Dr. Gale. With very great success. In eight hundred patients, I have lost but one.

[Pg 35]

Mr. Gatti sworn.

Couns. for the Pris. If I am properly instructed, you, Sir, have practised inoculation in France?

Mr. Gatti. Some time ago I was much employed in that business at Paris.

Couns. for the Pris. In what manner did you prepare your patients?

Mr. Gatti. I was always an enemy to any general plan: I paid the less regard to preparation, because I knew, that in all the Levant, where the natural small-pox is as fatal as elsewhere; and where you may find old women who have inoculated ten thousand people without an accident: the only enquiry is, whether the patient is prepared by nature. All that is considered, is, whether the breath be sweet, the skin soft, and whether a little wound in it heals easily. Whenever these conditions are found, they inoculate without the least apprehension of danger.

[Pg 36]

C. for the Pris. We shall now call a witness, who has already been examined by the counsel on the other side.

Mr. Chandler.